译ExpressionChangedAfterItHasBeenCheckedError.
译You'll encounter this error if your
code changes a value after change detection
has been run and the view has been built.
You'll only see this error in development
译because Angular runs an additional
change detection check to catch errors
like 译this that can cause erratic UI
behavior. The extra check ensures the
app is stable and that 译all data updates
have been reflected in the views. There
are a variety of reasons the view might
译be left in an inconsistent state, such
as code that updates the view during
the AfterViewInit 译lifecycle hook or
when change detection triggers itself
in an infinite loop, like a method that
译returns a different value each time,
or a child component that changes the
bindings on its parent.
译Let's start by looking at a simple
reproduction and solution.
译Then, we'll take a more detailed 译look
at Angular's change detection to understand
why this error happens and why it's important.
译Here in the app component template
we're using the ngIf directive with a
loading boolean. 译In the model, or our
component type script, we give it a default
value of true. Then, using 译the AfterViewInit
lifecycle hook we flip the value to false
when it's done loading. 译But when we
run this code we see ExpressionChangedAfterItHasBeenCheckedError:
译Previous value: false, Current value:
true. Now in a more complex app it might
not be 译clear where this error originates
from, but you can always assume that
it has 译something to do with a binding
in the template. In the stack trace you'll
find a link to the 译source map for the
component template that caused the error
and it takes us directly 译to the line
of code that caused the issue, which
is our ngIf binding to the loading boolean.
译What the error is trying to tell us
is that the loading value has changed
after the change 译detection cycle has
completed, but what exactly is wrong
with our code in this case? 译The short
answer is that we're using the wrong
lifecycle hook. 译If we move our code
from AfterViewInit to OnInit the error
goes 译away and everything works perfectly.
In other words, if you find yourself
updating 译values in AfterViewInit there's
a good chance that a simple refactor
to OnInit or the 译component constructor
will fix the issue. Okay, at this point
we know we used the wrong 译lifecycle
hook and we can fix it by refactoring,
but to really understand why let's do
a quick 译review of how change detection
works in Angular. The goal of change
detection is to 译keep the model, your
typescript code, in sync with the template,
your html. 译And it does so by looking
for data changes in the component tree
from top to bottom. 译First it checks
the parent, then the first child, second
child and so on, but if we update a 译binding
on the parent after it has already been
checked Angular will throw the error.
译Now what we have here is a simplified
breakdown of Angular's life cycle, or
the steps 译it performs when a component
is first initialized. First it updates
the bindings like 译the ngIf directive
in the template. Then it runs the OnInit
lifecycle 译hook, updates the DOM, then
runs change detection for the child component.
译Notice how the final step is AfterViewInit,
and more importantly that it 译runs after
change detection. Basically any code
that runs here 译should not attempt to
update the view and that was the root
of the problem in this case. 译Refactoring
to OnInit works great for initial values,
but if that doesn't fix the issue there
译are a few other ways you may have encountered
this error, along with additional ways
to fix it. 译In the component here, we're
using ViewChild to grab an element from
the DOM, but this 译element won't be
available until the AfterViewInit lifecycle
hook is called. 译But what if we can't
update the state of the component until
after we 译have the ViewChild element?
If we can't refactor to ngOnInit, 译we
have a couple of other options. An approach
you'll often see on StackOverflow 译answers
is to make the update asynchronous. When
we make the update async, it'll be 译picked
up on the next change detection check
and prevent the error from occurring.
译We can make it asynchronous by wrapping
it in a set timeout with a delay of zero.
That'll put 译the update in the next
macro task queue of the Javascript event
loop. Alternatively we can use 译a promise
that resolves immediately, then run the
update in its callback. This code will
achieve the 译same result, the only subtle
difference is that it runs on the micro
task queue before the end of 译the current
iteration in the browser's event loop.
Making the update asynchronous can 译work,
however it's very implicit and should
really only be used as a last resort.
译It's not clear why we make this code
asynchronous unless you understand the
nuances of Angular 译change detection
and the browser's event loop. Luckily
Angular provides us with a more direct
译and explicit way to trigger change
detection. We can manually trigger it
by injecting the change 译detector ref
in the constructor of the component.
We can then use it to manually run change
译detection by calling the detect changes
method. This will tell Angular to check
the view and 译its children, in which
case it will notice that our loading
state has changed, giving 译us yet another
way to address the error. Now an entirely
different way you might encounter 译this
error is when you have a method, usually
a getter, that doesn't return a predictable
value, 译which can cause an infinite
change detection loop. Take for example
this getter in our 译component that returns
a random number. If we try to use this
value in the 译template, Angular will
get a different value each time it's
checked. 译The solution in this case
is to make the method return a consistent
译value based on the state of the component.
In other words getters should be derived
译directly from the component state and
not values that change constantly 译like
timestamps or random numbers. Now let's
take a look at one more example, where
译we have both a parent and child component
at play. The app component the parent
contains the 译loading state just like
our previous examples, but instead of
running the update from the 译parent
component, we'll make it happen from
a child component with a custom event.
译In the item component, the child, we're
using the @Output decorator to create
译a custom event along with an event
emitter. Then during ngOnInit we'll go
ahead and 译emit the event with a value
of true. Then back in the app component
template we'll 译go ahead and declare
the item component. When it fires, we'll
set 译the loading value to false. The
end result is a situation where we have
a 译child component updating the parent
after change detection has already run
on the parent, 译and once again that
produces the error. A potential solution
in this case would be to 译move the loading
state into the child component and if
that's not possible you might consider
译moving this state to a shared service
where it can be injected in multiple
components.
译Let's finish up by doing a quick recap.
The ExpressionChangedAfterItHasBeenCheckedError
译occurs because a value in the template
has been updated after change detection
has finished. 译Debug it by first finding
the template in the stack trace. 译From
there you can analyze your code to determine
where the value is being updated and
use one of 译the methods covered in this
video to address it, such as refactoring
to the OnInit lifecycle 译hook, using
change detector ref manually, making
getters item potent, or making 译your
updates async as a last resort. Refer
to the Angular documentation 译for additional
details and examples.